Finding aid to the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00535
Sophia Smith Collection
- Byllye Avery Interviewed by Loretta J. Ross, July 21-22, 2005; Avery, Byllye; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 6)
  In this oral history, Byllye Avery describes her childhood in Georgia and Florida, her marriage to Wesley Avery, and her early widowhood, which propelled her into health activism in her early 30s. The interview focuses on her work in women's organizations in the 1970s, her experiences working with white women in the beginning of the women's health movement, and her experiences in establishing the premiere black women's health organization in the U.S., the National Black Women's Health Project (now known as the Black Women's Health Imperative). Avery's story proves she was an early pioneer in the women's health movement, as well as the most recognizable leader of the emerging movement of women of color working on reproductive health issues in the 1980s. She influenced an entire generation of activists while working to end reproductive health injustices experienced by all women. This interview was conducted the day before she married her long-time partner, Ngina Lythcott, who also participates in the interview. (Transcript 95 pp.)
  The Records of the Black Women's Health Imperative (formerly National Black Women's Health Project) are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Frances Beal Interviewed by Loretta J. Ross, March 18, 2005; Beal, Frances, 1940-; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 7)
  Frances Beal was born in Binghamton, NY, January 13, 1940, the daughter of Ernest Yates, who was of African American and Native American ancestry, and Charlotte Berman Yates, of radical Russian Jewish immigrant roots. When Fran's father died, her mother moved the family to St. Albans, an integrated neighborhood in Queens. In addition to observing her mother's participation in left politics, Fran was profoundly affected by the murder of Emmett Till. After graduating from Andrew Jackson High School in 1958, she became involved in civil rights activities and socialist politics while attending the University of Wisconsin. She married James Beal, and from 1959 to 1966, they lived in France, where they had two children and Fran became attuned to the internationalist/anti-imperialist politics of post-colonial African liberation struggles. During summers in the US in those years, she maintained connections with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). When her marriage ended and she returned to the United States in 1966, Beal took a job with the National Council of Negro Women, where she worked for a decade.
  In 1968 Beal co-founded the Black Women's Liberation Committee of SNCC and wrote one of the defining documents of black feminism, "Double Jeopardy: To Be Black and Female" (Sisterhood is Powerful, ed. Robin Morgan, 1970). The Committee quickly evolved into the Black Women's Alliance and soon, in order to include Puerto Rican women, into the Third World Women's Alliance (TWWA). TWWA rejected a feminism that posits sexism as the primary source of women's subordination and developed an analysis predicated on the interaction of race, class, and sex oppression and on an international perspective. Beal's work on gender, race and class laid the groundwork for current analyses of intersectionality. She became a member of the TWWA chapter in New York, where her organizing in the 1970s centered on abortion rights and sterilization abuse.
  In the 1980s Beal moved to California where she served as associate editor of The Black Scholar and wrote a weekly column in the San Francisco Bay View. In recent years she has worked with the National Anti-Racist Organizing Committee (NAROC) and with the Racial Justice Project of the ACLU of Northern California. She is the National Secretary of the Black Radical Congress. Beal lives in Oakland, where she continues to write.
  In this oral history, Frances Beal describes her unique childhood, born of parents of refugee Jewish, African American, and Native American descent. The interview focuses on her activism in the United States and in France, including founding the Women's Committee of SNCC (Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee). Beal's story captures the challenges of anti-racist, anti-fascist and anti-imperialist organizing with a gender perspective. (Transcript 54 pp.)
- Judith Berek Interviewed by Kathleen Banks Nutter, January 3-4, 2004; Berek, Judith, 1943-; Nutter, Kathleen Banks (Box 8, Box 9)
  Judith Berek was born in Brooklyn, New York, on April 8, 1943, the daughter of Ida Kantrowitz, a bookkeeper, and Leo Berek, a machinist at Brooklyn Navy Yard, later in its employee training area. Her father also was an ESOL teacher at night. Both parents graduated from Brooklyn College as night students, as did Berek herself. Her paternal grandfather taught her to sew. Berek has one brother, Peter, three years her senior. Raised a Jewish agnostic, Berek was briefly married in her twenties and has no children.
  She first worked as a lab tech (1962-68) at Kingsbrook Jewish Medical Center in Brooklyn. In 1968 Berek became an organizer for District 1199, National Union of Hospital and Healthcare Employees, AFL-CIO; she later served as vice-president and director of Legislative & Professional Programs, 1972-83. In 1983 Berek went to work for the State of New York Department of Social Services: until 1987 she was Director, Office of External Affairs, Special Assistant to the Commissioner on Intergovernmental Relations; from 1987 to 1991, Deputy Commissioner, Division of Adult Services, New York State DSS (both positions based in Albany). From 1991 to 1994, Berek worked for New York City Human Resources Administration as Executive Deputy Administrator for Personnel Administration. Since 1994, she has worked for the federal government in Medicare & Medicaid Services as a Senior Advisor (Washington, D.C., 1994-97), and Region II Coordinator (New York City, 1997-2002). Since 2002 Berek has been the Principal Advisor for National Policy Implementation, Office of the Administrator, Centers for Medicare & Medicaid Services, based in New York.
  In 1986 Berek managed Herman Badillo's campaign for New York State Comptroller and in 1989 was director of operations for David Dinkins' mayoral campaign. Throughout the 1970s and into the early 1980s, Berek was a founding member, board member, and co-chair of the National Legislative Committee, and president of the New York City chapter of the Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW).
  The oral history focuses on the various phases of Berek's life but is especially strong on her union activities within 1199 and the founding of CLUW. (Transcript 66 pp.)
- Brenda Berkman Interviewed by Kathleen Banks Nutter, February 2 and 6, 2004; Berkman, Brenda, 1951-; Nutter, Kathleen Banks (Box 10)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Researchers must have permission from Berkman to access this interview. Please contact Smith College Special Collections to secure permissions.
  Brenda Berkman was born October 19, 1951, in Asheville, North Carolina, and grew up in Richfield, Minnesota, the daughter of Ora (Bud) Berkman, a transportation specialist for the US Post Office, and Catherine Gray, a homemaker. She attended St. Olaf College in Northfield, Minnesota, graduating summa cum laude in 1973. She earned her M.A. in history from Indiana University in 1975 and a J.D. from New York University Law School in 1978.
  In 1978 Berkman filed suit in federal court against the Fire Department of the City of New York (FDNY) and the City, alleging sex discrimination in hiring (specifically, the physical agility exam for firefighter). By 1980 the Court certified the lawsuit as a class action on behalf of hundreds of women applicants who had taken the written portion of the exam. Berkman, however, was the sole named plaintiff and played an active role in that suit while simultaneously working as a lawyer specializing in immigration and employment law. In 1982, the Court ruled that the FDNY physical agility test was discriminatory and not job-related, and ordered the City and FDNY to develop a new job-related exam. The Firefighters' union appealed to the Second Circuit and lost that appeal. In 1982, Berkman and 46 other women were hired. Berkman and one other woman were fired after their probationary year. They brought suit to be re-hired and were reinstated under court order. Berkman rose through the ranks, and at the time of this interview was a Captain in Division 11 (Brooklyn).
  Berkman became the first professional firefighter to serve as a White House Fellow (1996-97). She received the NOW Woman of Courage award (2002). She was the founder and first President of the United Women Firefighters Association of NYC (1982) and President of Women in the Fire Service, a national organization. Berkman earned a MS in Fire Protection Management from John Jay College in 2001 and Executive Fire Officer certification from the National Fire Academy in 2006. She is featured in the video "Women of Ground Zero" and in "Taking the Heat," a documentary about her career, which aired on PBS in March, 2006. Captain Berkman continues to encourage the recruitment, hiring, and retention of women firefighters around the world. In 2007, there are only 28 women among more than 11,000 members of the FDNY. Captain Berkman retired from the FDNY as the Captain of Engine 239 (Brooklyn) in September, 2006.
  The oral history focuses on the various phases of Berkman's life but is especially strong on her efforts to join the Fire Department of New York which resulted in a class action suit that in 1982 forced the City of New York to open the fire department ranks to women. (Transcript 47 pp.)
- Michaelann Bewsee interviewed by Joyce Follet, May 16-17, 2005; Bewsee, Michaelann, 1947-; Follet, Joyce (Box 11)
  Michaelann Bewsee was born December 21, 1947, in Springfield, Massachusetts. The daughter of Emery Martin Bewsee and Ann Marie (Davison) Bewsee, she was the eldest of four children in a working-class Catholic family. After serving in the military, her father worked as a civil engineer for town highway departments. Her mother worked in area department stores until children's chronic illnesses, including Michaelann's rheumatic fever, forced her to stay at home. Home-tutored until her early teens, Michaelann then attended Catholic school, graduating from Cathedral High School in 1964.
  A single mother at the age of 19, Michaelann moved to Boston where she did clerical, factory, and waitressing work. She spent the next few years searching for personal, spiritual, and political moorings while involved in communal living arrangements and social movements. She was a foot soldier for the ERA and cooked for the Black Panther Party's free breakfast program. Michaelann struggled with poverty in these years, and, against her will, Michaelann's parents took custody of her daughter. Beginning in 1973, Michaelann and a partner homesteaded in Maine. When that relationship ended in 1977, Michaelann moved back to Springfield, pregnant with a second daughter. After a few years on public assistance, she began work as a decisional trainer with prison inmates.
  Bewsee continued political activism. She became involved with the Hampden County Peace Coalition (1980-83), the Communist Labor Party (1981-85), the Rainbow Coalition (1983-89), and the McKnight Neighborhood Council (1980-86). She also joined a few other women on public assistance to protest welfare policies. In 1985 their efforts led to the formation of Arise for Social Justice, where Bewsee remains a key leader.
  Arise is a grassroots "poor people's rights organization" whose purpose is "to learn to speak for ourselves to advocate for positive changes in the treatment of poor people and in the welfare system." Most members are women who are or have been on welfare and who come from diverse racial, ethnic and educational backgrounds. The group aims to educate, organize, and unite poor people to know and stand up for their rights, to educate the community to its common interest in economic justice for poor people, to educate low-income people about and encourage their participation in the political process, and to promote self-esteem among low-income people. Recent high-profile activities include sponsoring a tent city for the homeless, running a controversial needle exchange program, suing the city for its at-large system of representation, and protesting construction of a new women's prison.
  Bewsee describes a quiet, book-filled childhood restricted by chronic illness. She details a young adulthood immersed in the counterculture of the 1960s and 1970s and recounts the trauma of losing custody of her daughter. Much of the oral history focuses on Arise and the challenges of grassroots organizing, including the struggle to promote radical popular education while serving immediate needs, with specific attention to organizing around homelessness. (Transcript 100 pp.)
  The Arise for Social Justice Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Joan E. Biren (JEB) Interviewed by Kelly Anderson, February 27-28, 2004; Biren, Joan E.; Anderson, Kelly (Box 12)
  Joan E. Biren (b.1944) grew up in Washington D.C., graduated from Mount Holyoke College in 1966, and pursued graduate training at both Oxford University and the American University. Biren joined the women's liberation movement in D.C. in 1969. One of the first out lesbians in the movement, Biren and others (including Rita Mae Brown and Charlotte Bunch) formed a lesbian-separatist collective, the Furies, in 1971. Though the collective was short-lived, it had, through its publications, a significant impact on the strategies of the women's movement.
  Biren is best known for her photographic portraits, some of the earliest documents of late 20th-century lesbian life. Realizing the need for affirming images and self-expression outside of traditional patriarchal language, her work has appeared in off our backs, The Washington Blade, Gay Community News, and on countless album and book covers. Biren has published two ground-breaking collections of her photography: Eye to Eye: Portraits of Lesbians (1979) and Making A Way: Lesbians Out Front (1987). In the 1990s, Biren turned from photography to filmmaking. She documented the 1987 and 1993 gay and lesbian marches on Washington and recently completed an award-winning film on lesbian pioneers Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon.
  In this oral history Biren describes growing up in a Jewish family in Washington D.C., her education, and her entrance into activism. She reflects on the nuances of class and ethnicity, both in mainstream institutions and in the movement, and on her coming-out process. Biren describes her role in the Furies, the dynamics of the collective and the aftermath of its dissolution, reflecting on its impact on her life and on the larger movement. The interview also focuses on Biren's cultural activism and her work as a photographer. Biren describes the process of finding subjects, her intentions behind the work, and the impact of her photographs. She concludes with a discussion of her current work as a filmmaker in the gay and lesbian community. (Transcript 90 pp.)
  The Joan E. Biren Papers are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Linda Burnham interviewed by Loretta J. Ross, March 18, 2005; Burnham, Linda; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 13)
  Linda Burnham (b. 1948) grew up in Brooklyn, New York, the child of parents active in the Young Communist League in the 1930s and 1940s. She graduated from Reed College in 1968. As a journalist and political activist, Burnham has been involved with the Venceremos Brigades, the Third World Women's Alliance, the Alliance Against Women's Oppression, the Angela Davis Defense Committee, and the Line of March. She co-founded the Women of Color Resource Center in Oakland, California, in 1989. Her recent writings focus on women and poverty and on women and militarism.
  In this oral history, Linda Burnham describes her childhood immersed in the black radical community of New York City in the 1950s and 1960s. It also includes a brief interview with her mother, Dorothy Burnham. Linda's interview focuses on her activism in the early abortion rights movement in Black Women United in the 1970s and the impact working with the Venceremos Brigade and traveling to Cuba had on her life. She also discusses the anti-imperialist work that led her to San Francisco in the 1960s, to New York in the 1970s, and back to the Bay Area in the 1980s, where she founded the Women of Color Resource Center, which she still directs. (Transcript 54 pp.)
- Kathleen Casavant interviewed by Kathleen Banks Nutter, January 13-14, 2004; Casavant, Kathleen, 1951-; Nutter, Kathleen Banks (Box 14)
  Per the narrator's request, portions of this interview are closed until 14 Jan 2029, and the transcript of the interview cannot be posted online. Contact Special Collections for access to a redacted transcript.
  Kathleen Casavant was born in Taunton, Massachusetts, July 27, 1951, the daughter of May Theresa Brown, factory worker, waitress, school bus driver, and deli cook (still living), and Arthur J. Morin, Jr., a house painter who also worked as a painter at General Dynamics Shipyard (deceased). She has three younger brothers. Kathy attended parochial school through the eighth grade and graduated from Bridgewater-Raynham Regional High School in 1969. In 1998 she earned her B.S. through the Labor Studies Program at University of Massachusetts, Boston. She has been married for 30 years to Arnold Casavant, a teacher in Easton, Massachusetts. They have one son, born in 1982.
  After high school, Casavant worked a variety of clerical jobs until going to work for the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, first as comptroller (1978-82) and then as an organizer, secretary-treasurer, and union representative (1982-98). When the Amalgamated merged with the International Ladies Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) in 1995 to become UNITE, she was elected secretary-treasurer of the New England chapter. In 1995, Casavant became the first woman ever to be elected to executive vice-president of the Massachusetts AFL-CIO, making history again in 1998 when she was elected treasurer, second in command of the Massachusetts AFL-CIO. In 1985, she became active in WILD (Women in Leadership Development) and still serves on its board.
  The oral history focuses on the various phases of Casavant's life but is especially strong on her union activities, both as an organizer and as a union leader. (Transcript 76 pp.)
- Linda Chavez-Thompson interviewed by Kathleen Banks Nutter, February 9-10, 2004; Chavez-Thompson, Linda, 1944-; Nutter, Kathleen Banks (Box 15)
  Linda Chavez-Thompson was born August 3, 1944, in Lubbock, Texas, one of eight children born to Felipe and Genoveva Chavez; her father worked as a cotton sharecropper. She joined her parents in the cotton fields at the age of ten, quit school at 16 and went to work. Married for the first time at age 20 to Jose Luz Ramirez, she continued working as a domestic and had two children. In 1967, at the age of 23, she went to work for the Laborers' International Union and served as the secretary for the Lubbock local and, as the only Spanish-speaking union officer, represented all the Hispanic American workers within the local. Four years later she went to work for the American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees Union (AFSCME) in San Antonio and rose through the ranks to be international vice-president (1988-96). In 1995 Chavez-Thompson was elected executive vice-president (third-ranking officer) of the AFL-CIO, the first woman and the first person of color to hold such a high office within the AFL-CIO; she was re-elected in 1997 and in 2001. She also serves as a vice-chair of the Democratic National Committee and an executive committee member of the Congressional Hispanic Caucus Institute. She married for a second time in 1985 to Robert Thompson, now deceased.
  The oral history focuses on the various phases of Chavez-Thompson's life but is especially strong on her union activities, both as an organizer and as a union leader. (Transcript 53 pp.)
- Katsi Cook interviewed by Joyce Follet, October 26-27, 2005; Cook, Katsi; Follet, Joyce (Box 16)
  At the request of the narrator, portions of this interview are closed until January 4, 2035. A redacted transcript is available online and in the reading room.
  Sherrill Elizabeth Tekatsitsiakwa (Katsi) Cook was born January 4, 1952, the youngest of four children of Evelyn Kawennaien Mountour Cook of Kanawake, Quebec, and William John Cook, both enrolled members of the St. Regis Mohawk Tribe. Katsi's mother was educated by Catholic nuns. Her father, a Dartmouth grad, was a Captain in the U.S. Marines and a World War II fighter pilot. Her mother and father died when Katsi was a child. Katsi grew up in the Akwesasne community on the St. Regis Reservation, which straddles the U.S. - Canada border along the St. Lawrence River. She describes Akwesasne in her youth as "a reservation community of subsistence fisher-people, gardeners, herbalists and midwives." She attended private Catholic boarding schools but began participating in longhouse culture as a teen.
  Cook attended Skidmore College from 1970 to 1972, then transferred into the first class of women accepted at Dartmouth College. She soon left college to become involved in the American Indian Movement (AIM).
  After a brief first marriage and first child, she married José Barreiro, a Cuban-born activist and academic. In the early 1970s, and again in the 1980s, Cook and Barreiro worked with the Kenienkehaka Longhouse Council of Chiefs at Akwesasne, where she was Women's Health Editor of Akwesasne Notes, a clearinghouse of information for the emerging Indian consciousness movement. She toured the U.S. and Canada with White Roots of Peace, a group she describes as a traveling university through which participants learned Native knowledge from elders and imparted it to others.
  Cook sought out traditional birthing methods as she prepared for the birth of her first child in 1975. She took up midwifery after participating in the 1977 conference at Loon Lake, NY, where traditional chiefs, clan mothers, and young activists from the Six Nations worked to define sovereignty for Native peoples; they identified control of reproduction as one of its essential elements. In 1978 she did an apprenticeship in spiritual midwifery at The Farm in Tennessee, followed by clinical training at the University of New Mexico Women's Health Training Program. She was struck by Pueblo and Navajo women's lack of knowledge regarding reproduction in general and Native birthing traditions in particular, and recognized this loss of self-knowledge and cultural ways as a consequence of colonization. This awareness, coupled with community concern about the sterilization of Native women, led Cook to reclaim childbirth as key to community healing and survival, a process of empowerment through which women revive indigenous culture and restore Native peoples' connections to ancestral land.
  After moving to South Dakota, Cook became active in AIM. In September, 1978, she attended the founding meeting of Women of All Red Nations (WARN). She then worked at the Red Schoolhouse Clinic, a WARN project in Minneapolis-St. Paul, where she trained an Anishnabe Birthing Crew and created the Women's Dance Health Program.